[Music]
in the middle of this ongoing crisis the
question of who to trust how to find
truth free speech and censorship a
taking center stage to explore these
issues I thought the best person to
speak to would be Douglas Murray the
associate editor of The Spectator
magazine and the author of the
bestsellers the strange death of Europe
and the recent madness of crowds so we
discussed the censorship of the big tech
platforms these people have got
unbelievable power and and they're not
worthy of it
I haven't thought seriously about any
issues certainly not about this one
certainly not about censorship says you
know about free speech certainly not
about how you hold the keys to the
world's thinking the decline of the
traditional media one thing I don't
think has got enough attention in recent
years is the extent to which no public
discussion is genuinely taking us
forward on main platforms I'm genuinely
worried about this that no discussion
show on the BBC or anywhere else
actually solves anything doesn't even
get close and what's the reason for that
the reason is that that's not the aim
anymore the aim is to have a piece of
theater and we also talked about the
issues raised by the recent rebel wisdom
investigation into David Icke and London
real
I saw your video on Brian Rose and
London real hmm and I was glad you
picked up on that that was a fascinating
corner in all of this Douglass thank you
for joining me it's a great pleasure
yeah so we we've spoken before a couple
of times from the channel and we haven't
talked about your latest book madness of
crowds we talked about strange death of
Europe and massive crowds really really
interesting in it you kind of look at
the way the media portrays certain
perspective you want to give us a very
quick Pressy of what madness of crowds
is about before you go into a little bit
of the detail sure the madness of crowds
came out late last year it's coming out
in paperback in September and it's about
what I regard is being all
crowd madnesses of our time the identity
issues that have roiled through our
societies of course since it came out
we've had different types of madness to
sin in our societies and so in a way the
interesting thing in this moment to me
is you know what is holding up in that
and what seems already to be positively
historical you know and and that's
because you know I I was I was saying as
I was writing it and I say in the book I
mean these things of group identities
based on race gender sexuality and so on
are are shallow identities which are
themselves the products of a vacuum
which I described in my previous book
but I always thought that the
discussions on privilege and
microaggressions and all of this stuff
that we were forced to hear about in the
daily basis was the product of a society
that was rich and comfortable and didn't
have enough to moan about because you
can only moan about microaggressions if
you live in a society where there's very
little aggression I've heard a few
people say that the virus has killed
work I'm very wary of simply using the
virus as a justification for your
pre-existing hopes and I think an awful
lot of people have done that you know
that mean people who said well this is
the end of this or the beginning of that
the triumph of this and and it's always
a cough it always completely accords
with their pre-existing views and so I'm
just wary of that it did occur to me I'm
not immune to that myself it did occur
to me at the beginning of this virus
well perhaps we'll hear a little less
from the whoa crowd I can't deny that I
expect that wider society might have a
little less time for it now but but that
might just be me in imposing a hope on
this but nevertheless I mean it you know
the recession that we're already
in is a time when an awful lot of
families in countries like ours are
going to be suffering and seeing a
fall-off in their lifestyles and you
know considerable unemployment and all
of the problems that come from that and
I just I think I think it's unlikely
that in that era we're going to spend as
much time talking about what Sam Smith
wants to be called today but but that
won't mean that people like that don't
keep doing that yeah I mean there's one
there's one topic that I've really
wanted to talk to you about since I read
madness of crowds and that's subtle
differences that I'm picking up between
the UK and the u.s. attitude to a lot of
these topics and because I get the sense
that there is quite subtle but quite
important differentiations of the
policing of these kind of arguments in
the UK in the u.s. I'm going to use the
trans example because I think it is a
very illustrative example here with the
Guardian UK edition brought out a very
kind of vanilla leader article that said
we've got to understand that there are
differing factors at play there are
trade-offs for example around gender
identity and also same-sex attraction
and that what has historically been the
the defense of gay rights is threatened
by the the rejection of gender identity
of trans etc just just laying out that
there are different factors at play and
that was rejected wholesale by the
Guardians us staff as being transphobic
and I get I get this sense that both in
the UK and the US this is a hugely
polarizing a hugely activating debate
but there seems to be more of a healthy
debate in my view in the UK maybe
because of our history of kind of
radical feminism in the Labor Party but
there's a slightly different background
I'm picking up subtle differences that
in the u.s. if you deviate from a
certain kind of fixed ideology you're
put beyond the pale it's not just beyond
the pale issues that you get put on a
particular political side that's what's
important
is that I mean obviously the ideal is
that we don't have identity issue we
don't have actual rights issues fought
through the prism of a different
political issue so the ideal would be
that that what-what legitimate claims
there are within the trans issue do not
have to be translated through the prism
of whether or not you're pro or anti
Donald Trump is a very bad way to
discuss that if you actually want to
discuss the fascinating issue which
which I'm surprised the Guardian dared
to venture into or vote autogain
affiliate of whether or not trans is to
do with sexual attraction and sexual
kick or not very very interesting issue
very dangerous issue then then you would
hope you could have that very important
and finely balanced discussion without
having to use Donald Trump as the
dividing line I mean awful why would you
and the answer is just that the America
is stuck in the same position that
Britain was stuck in until I'd say
December the 12th last year where it
where everything in Britain was seen
through the brexit prism and everything
became a culture war to do with brexit
you know America can't even have the
coronavirus without having the debate
through the prism of Donald Trump and
whether it's going to be helpful for his
re-election or not and that's that's why
you don't you just can't have a
discussion it was bad enough in America
already because they had this endless
thing of whether you were a Republican
or a Democrat and you know there's a
growing number of people quite rightly
in the u.s. who realized that was a that
is a really not helpful prism on a lot
of issues not all issues on a lot of
issues and so yeah I I'm worried about
this because all the America is the most
important country in the world it's its
cultural impact for good and ill is
global in a way that no other countries
so and and I do think that a lot of the
problems that we've seen on the identity
questions in recent years have to a
great extent come about because we have
imported parts of the American debate
you know we've imported parts of the
American race debate to the UK in a way
which I think has been massively
deleterious for the UK and and you know
it matters when when the major democracy
in the world has a debate this bad and
public thinking so poor yeah you're
already going into the area that I was
hoping to go into next and I do I get
this sense that the pandemic certainly
the the fault lines exposing in America
and the way that it seems to be kind of
accelerating almost like a catalyst of
the already existing culture war seems
existential to me almost in a way that
but it doesn't in the UK and you had an
interview recently with Joe where I
think politics Joe I think it was when
you pointed out how the UK in the u.s.
are reacting very differently to this
and I think it's really interesting to
drill down into why that might be
because there was also this sense for a
long time you pointed out that the UK
had very similar fault lines we didn't
trust our experts we we didn't trust the
media all of these same fault lines but
actually since the pandemic has struck
there's been this sense of kind of some
kind of I don't know sobering up in a
way in the UK that has happened in the
u.s. I agree I mean I think that i think
that Boris Johnson has been able to call
on goodwill that we didn't know was
there until recently or we'd forgotten
was there I think that is partly to do
with him partly to do with his his
history I think that if the Conservative
Party at this stage had been led by a
highly authoritarian right-wing figure
who looked like he really wanted to lock
the British people in our homes I think
we wouldn't have agreed with such
alacrity and this this of all of the
detractors all the criticism he comes in
for I do think that is worth remembering
I think that Britain is in a healthy ish
position on that we're not in a healthy
position economically but then no one is
but but we we have trust in the experts
by the way there is a huge caveat coming
there isn't there which I'm sure you can
feel as I can feel which is what if what
if the experts are shown to have got
this very significantly wrong or have
have got them their predictions way out
I'm starting to think that that is the
case perhaps I'm slow to the party on
that but I think most of us are starting
to notice that that the virus is clearly
worse than some people have been
pretending and not as bad as we first
feared and if it does turn out that the
the scientists got it wrong at the
beginning I worry the what trust we have
just refound in expertise is about to be
lost in a way that that it hasn't been
since I know our loss of trust in the
intelligence community after the WI WMD
issue in 2003 so that that does worry me
but but yes broadly speaking we are in a
better place in America where where
people don't don't half the country
doesn't trust the president at all and
and I think certainly in some sections
would be happy for the economy to crash
as long as it crashes on Donald Trump's
watch and therefore he doesn't get
reelected yeah I mean certainly true
that Trump is a factor like Trump from
sort of derangement syndrome as people
have talked about I think exist on both
sides by Pro and ante yeah but I wonder
if there's other factors as well this
sense of this sort of I get the sense of
a civic space in the UK that's just
outside of the dynamics of polarization
and there's all sorts of reasons for
that I think that I wonder whether the
BBC has something to do with that but
there is at least some some center of
power that is not being pulled one side
or the other by Corp
factors and by the sort of polarization
spiral what do you what what else do you
think might be behind these two
different yeah I think it's that I think
I think I have to say this is this is a
point I've made a few times in recent
weeks and it's it's it's in some ways a
very obvious one which is just that we
do have some institutions that are above
politics the clearest and most obvious
of which is the monarchy and full of
criticisms that levelled by the
Republicans in the UK I think they've
had a hell of a virus you know the Queen
was about the only figure we really
wanted to give her take in the early
weeks and I do think that you know as a
small C conservative I I'm I'm
encouraged by that because conservatism
in the way I understand it has an awful
lot to do with institutions and that's
that's built on the idea that
institutions reflect the public and and
and that they are they are reflexive
things that the public gives trust to
the institution and the institution
gives trust to the public and that
they're complimentary and of course it
means that people are loyal to
institutions that are loyal to them but
these bonds are incredibly important and
maybe they aren't built up overnight you
know the bond that does does exist for
all the criticisms I and many others
level at them with the BBC there is a
level of trust that means that when
something pandemic something like that
occurs you know we we do turn on the BBC
that something like the VE Day
celebrations last week the BBC does the
job you know and and that's that's very
important but you know that the central
insight of conservatism on this is of
course is that such trust takes an
awfully long time to build and that
important and significant meaningful
institutions take a very long time to
build
with the rider that of course they can
be destroyed very easily I mean it would
be it would be extremely easy to deer
ass innate the public space but at times
like this you would recognize I hope
some of the consequences had that have
happened you know if if the cut and if
the United Kingdom had to wait on the
the first speech by president kinegg
about the virus where he could reflect
on his lessons from nineteen eighties
Labour Party politics or something I
don't think the country would be and
remotely as healthier condition as it is
and I think you can do that on the whole
range of institutions but I don't sound
glib about it but or you know I don't I
don't think it's I don't think it's rosy
now it's interesting you bring up the
idea of institutions because the other
thing that I'm really interested to talk
to you about is the sort of the
influence of the tech platforms because
what we are what we have been saying in
in the media is this huge kind of
washing away of a lot of institutional
memory and a lot of institutional
standards we have this whole thing about
the tech platform suddenly making them
the realization that they are actually
publishers well they have to take on
some responsibility as publishers and I
speak as someone who's been part of
channel for being part of the BBC and
then kind of gone outside and made my
own films and really enjoyed the freedom
to to look at narratives that are often
excluded by the mainstream and and
realize the value of that perspective
but also being sort of terrified by the
spread of misinformation and the kind of
it feels like a very dangerous I've kind
of called it an interregnum we've had
this sort of we were in this
institutional framework that has now
been kind of washed away and we don't
yet have I could imagine a kind of more
decentralized way of finding truth of
sort of like I don't know some kind of
but we're not there we sort of seem to
be in a very dangerous place while we're
in this interregnum and there's no real
gatekeepers and there's no real way of
asserting what's true anymore
it it actually does have a significant
similarity with the issue they brought
earlier about the brexit and Trump issue
you know my sadness about both of these
issues in recent years has been the
opportunity cost of the opponents of
these realities avoiding the opportunity
to learn from something one of the major
things is they lost the opportunity to
recognize that the American public voted
for Donald Trump despite everything that
they knew about him in 2016 it's the
same thing with the brexit thing you
know I happen to be in favor of brexit
like the majority of the British public
but I just I think it was a massive
mistake of people who voted the other
way to have lost to miss the opportunity
for years to recognize that day had
missed something they've got something
wrong they massively misread something
and maybe the population were under
something and it's the same thing with
the media issue you just raise the
question is why the mainstream media
doesn't learn from what it keeps missing
why there's so much that it just can't
do why doesn't it why doesn't it listen
to that and I and I know as I'm sure you
do individuals in all the major channels
who know that they've been missing
something and they know they've been
missing something out they feel it and
make their and they but as an author as
an institutional level they don't know
what to do about that and and and I I
just think that they've they've they've
missed something and it's it's not just
them as I say it's common it's a common
issue of our time some kind of inability
to ameliorate facts and truths that
should have been ameliorated by now I
completely agree and we've put out quite
a lot of pieces around that like what
the mainstream is missing and how
critical that is the the fact that
they're missing it and being completely
surprised by things they didn't expect
is is like an existential problem but I
also I'm wondering whether you also have
some concerns as I do of the as I'm
seeing
conspiracy theories rising
misinformation rising is sort of on the
other side of that kind of that pendulum
real concerns as well
I saw your video on Brian Rose and
London real hmm
and I was glad you picked up on that
that was a fascinating corner in all of
this and it speaks very much to you the
concern you've just expressed yeah I'm
glad you saw that yeah what did you make
I tried to bring in all of the wider
issues which is my concern is that if if
somehow we don't find a way of self
policing that we're going to get really
heavy hand of tech censorship that is
not going to be able to buy I just don't
I just don't trust any of these tech
platforms to be able to make editorial
decisions know about how well something
is being treated and how much editorial
value there is in treating something so
they're going to squash my fears that
they'll squash all alternative
narratives one desperately need
alternative narratives to reboot a lot
of our systems well there are two
particular ways I think into it into
trying to sort that out the first is to
think that the people currently
populating the firms are not up to the
task the second is they wouldn't be
whoever they are but let's take the
first one first
the massive problem on this with the
tech companies in the US and the UK is
the fact that they have been in in both
countries flooded by partisans of a
particular political side so it's in the
wake of the Obama the exit of the Obama
regime that Obama government rather I
should say differently to say sounds I
know the body of the Obama government
when it when that administration left
power the you know so many people went
straight into Silicon Valley and got
very well remunerated jobs there and
that's one of the reasons why you see
the particular direction of the of the D
monetization
and all that sort of thing there and
something very similar happened in the
UK I mean since the Liberal Democrats
were very nearly wiped out not quite
nearly enough my taste that and Nick
Clegg lost his job and so on and went to
Facebook it's the same thing Facebook's
filled with Liberal Democrats these
people are not up the task that they're
a very significant number of them if not
all them a very low grade I haven't
thought seriously about any issues
certainly not about this one certainly
not about censorship setting not about
free speech certainly not about how you
hold the keys to the world's thinking
and whether how you tread through that
era they haven't thought about any of
that but they have a few existing
pre-existing political views and you and
unfortunately the way of both in the US
and the UK that that expresses itself is
the fact that they have this weird idea
that there is sort of you know you can
tackle extremism for instance as a thing
rather than particular manifestations of
it that are particularly close to the
boat it seeks to deal with hate you know
I mean I mean how how much of a
combination of Big Brother and
kindergarten can you put up with we're
going to deal with hate oh yeah or human
emotion are you going to deal with next
week your take do you want to take
lustfulness hmm how about let's do
gluttony next month
how about envy pride pride let's go
through them all yeah we the tech
platforms are gonna have a war on pride
I hate I mean really and from that once
you've decided that your self-appointed
task is to tackle hate well it means
among other things you'll take out some
things that are true and and you'll
you'll go for I mean the problem on this
I'm sure it's personal for me as it is
for you the problem on all this is we've
repeatedly seen how close
our own boats these people are willing
to come you know not to me not to you
but people we think should be in the
discussion sometimes people we know of
spoken with who you know you discover
reviewed by YouTube or something as
totally reprehensible characters on a
par with some kind of Nazi you know III
mean this is obviously part of a wider
language and political slippage you know
in our own lifetimes far-right has come
to be a term which instead of being used
very specifically and necessarily on
occasion has become just something can
call anyone if you don't like them much
want to do them a bit of harm you know
and and and these people have got
unbelievable power and and then they're
not worthy of it
but that comes the second buy which is
is it possible for anyone to do that
even if Eric and load rather brilliant
people were in charge of it could they
do it could could you do it could I do
it I don't know I mean I I think to a
great extent this is the problem of this
is this second bit hoo-hoo-hoo and earth
would you give the right to police the
Internet to you know who's your
candidate you do you think I mean this
is the other issue is that especially on
YouTube there's such a kind of free
speech absolutism so people kind of deny
the need for any placing whatsoever
which to me seems naive especially when
you come I think a good example recently
is like okay we're dealing with
something like medical cures we have
regulations around kind of miracle cures
for example because we know if someone
claims to be able to cure cancer someone
is gonna be desperate enough to go to
them like their I'm interested as well
are you a free speech absolutist or if
not what is it this feels like an
impossible algorithm to me so the
problem is is that it shifts the obvious
limit on freedom of speech anyone I
agree with it in incitement
but incitement has to have an incredible
a specific definition and it does by the
way in law I mean it's not impossible
this the incitement laws in a country
like Britain a pretty good I mean you
can't you can't go to prison or be
prosecuted for saying I think X person
should die it might be an unwise use of
words unkind use of words but that's not
the same thing as standing with a mob
outside person's house and saying to the
mob go get them
that's incitement that's incitement and
and the law recognizes that is not it's
not impossible not starting from year
zero in any of this country again to the
expectations of a lot of people who seem
to go and work at YouTube and Google and
so that is where I draw the line I think
that the very interesting one on cures
which you raise is is tricky because it
comes close to that doesn't it i I have
to say I can't deny I have a certain
free song of enjoyment when I see total
hucksters behaving as they have
throughout history in our own time I
just as a historian I find it
fascinating
you know the very beginning of this
corona crisis there was that there's a
guy or the what's his name he's been
married to Tammy Faye and he was a
huckster preacher in the US and he went
to prison in the nineties you know for
the usual reasons and and televangelists
and and you know no one had heard from
him a couple of decades and now better
the corona crisis comes along back he
pops onto some network in America
claiming that his files of of something
with silver in them are the only cure
for crow and I just I look at this with
a sir I can't deny certain sort of joy
that such a figure as Chaucer wrote
about should be existing throughout
human history always always those people
are they're always there with us and
there is something and so there is
something any radical about
which is one of the most important
things I think in in finding cents and
our place in the universe is always to
try to reconcile with ourselves with the
things we can do nothing about and to
recognize them to recognize there will
always be hucksters and frauds and
chances and fakers and we can't
eradicate that we cannot give them
platforms definitely we can try to
expose them for sure but we kind of
Radek ated those people and those people
are gonna take in some people it's
impossible that they were they wouldn't
at some stage and so so when I but the
one that obviously which you talked
about on which which is very alarming is
this one this one of the ike thing
because you know i I said it some of the
other day when they drop this subject up
but when I was interviewed by the man
from London real who had liked and an
interesting interview he mentioned David
Icke to me he said oh that seems I think
David Icke you know David Icke said to
me recent and I sort of you know what
you know I mean I that yeah and I just
thought I never been to the station I've
seen it but I thought what are you doing
in between David Icke yeah I have no
interest in the man who I last saw I
think on whoa good wasn't it declaring
himself to be Jesus I don't keep a very
close eye on people once they've
declared themselves to be Jesus I turn
away and so somebody citing some of that
now but again it's to do with a it's to
do not just with the issue of platforms
it's to do with societal health the
problem is that at some level we periods
like this show up how healthy or not our
fort is and I think it's done pretty
well I think that by and large British
society and other that we don't actually
go to David Icke for Corona
advice but there is this issue of what
if at a at a moment equivalent to the
person standing outside the person's
house saying go get them at a moment of
real international and a national crisis
somebody is flogging an idea like you
know the one that Ike was about five G
masts and so on and and what if that
does lead to people laying those cables
being attacked and things being burnt
down those are things we see throughout
history and they happen all the time
during epidemics and periods where
people are frightened and I think I've
got faith that they can be countered I
don't think we need anything wildly
authoritarian about that I just I
genuinely don't think that if David Icke
is put into a discussion with somebody
who knows what they're talking about
that he can win I think there's no
chance of it I think he's a sign of
slight ill health that somebody with his
track record could in any way catch on
at a time like this I agree and I kind
of veer between so there's also it's not
just I there's also various other people
that are saying the same things that are
getting more like fringe medical figures
for example who are getting a lot more
prominent saying certain things about
the virus being a hoax or and my my
concern about that if I from from this
side my concern is that they seem to be
within kind of self-enclosed ecosystems
with no accountability sure this is a
dynamic of the fact that we used to have
a system where with fewer media channels
the accountability worked because you
had a certain number of media channels
you have a certain number of voices they
would be held to account now it seems
it's possible for these completely
self-enclosed bubbles to exist when no
one has to face a contrary position no
one has to face a tough interviewer am i
worried that that dynamic just seems to
be accelerating that we've lost any kind
of systemic
accountability I think that's my concern
but I don't but over there between
thinking that's a real huge problem and
between thinking well actually that it's
not going to influence that many people
and I think you're right to be concerned
about it and I think there are times
when that concern feels more alive than
at others and I think a few weeks ago
you know and actually in certain places
now with people trying to you know
breaking lock downs and all that
something you can feel population being
becoming restive we can all feel that a
restless rather we can all feel that and
I've no doubt that there will be some
movements and individuals who take
advantage of that and there will be
misinformation and disinformation passed
around I'm not as worried about it at
the moment as I say I am worried if
there is a massive reputational hit
taken by experts deservedly because
that's when people go elsewhere but a
lot of this also is people in having fun
I think it's I think it's a an easily
passed over element of it that people
are attracted to slightly dangerous
things you know I once said I once said
to Clive James talking about poetry and
I remember saying to Clive oh you know
you know how how would you get more
young people falling in love with poetry
like you did as a young boy growing up
in Australia in the 1940s he said ban
the stuff make it illegal impose long
prison sentences if you're caught with
with it and you know the truth in that
that of course you tell something to
tell people that something is dangerous
or has been banned and you send people
to it
why not because they're all going to
believe it but because as some of the
might but a large number of just going
there for the kicks and for the
curiosity you know and and and again
we've had that that discussion with the
banning of books if it's not just
decades we've had it for centuries we
have been through all of this argument
before
and an I reiterate I'm I'm concerned by
the fact that people up people aren't
drawing on knowledge that we already
have you know I I think that John Stuart
Mill and Milton a useful guides on this
I don't see why we've got to learn it
all again this kind of Silicon Valley
exceptionalism as well the sort of sense
that these are problems no one's ever
dealt with before that's right that's
because so many of the people working
there are kids and and have no knowledge
of history and think that they're in
some unique place and now I mean I yeah
I'm glad you watched the the London real
piece because for me there's just so
many issues that it brings up what I
have what I have been quite pleased
about is I'm seeing so I put out my
pieces I think one other one other
YouTube channel kind of picked up when
it has been doing sort of regular
updates as well what I've seen in the
last day or two especially is a real
turning of his audience against sort of
at least a questioning in the comments
that it seems that that kind of immune
response seems to be working yeah well
made Emilia allegedly made a million
bucks we don't know it was on his
website but then he he's just started
another crowd funder for another 250 per
month to keep it running and that seems
to have kind of sent him over the edge
with his own audience so so what I'm
seeing now I think here is this sort of
immune response or at least this
accountability starting to kick in a bit
more yes and I think that's I think
that's perfect healthy it's happened
before it'll happen again
there'll be lots of people who try to to
use you know the opportunity to do a
sort of bank raid and and and and I
think that their readers their consumers
their followers will resent it just as
much as when that has happened with
older media I don't see it in any way
being that new
are there any other issues that came up
from that piece that these thought work
well I think I think that that central
thing you're over you're over in it
which is how we agree on how we can
agree on what is true in the current era
is is the is one of the central is one
of the central issues and this is a
problem which you've seen and I've seen
firsthand with the mainstream media
which is to do with the issue of balance
the massive risk that goes on at the
moment is that everything that is known
to be true is also known to have a
counterbalance and that the
counterbalance is given equal weight and
this is this is a great concern it's a
great concern scientific community it's
a great concern as far than in every
thinking community and the internet
definitely makes that tough because of
the enormous ease with which people can
access things I let me give you one
example in an area I know a fair amount
about there are people on the American
right very reprehensible figures the
Louvre and figures who have been playing
with claims that for instance you know
to talk about the Holocaust and to
question it is to bring incredible risk
and danger to yourself
I reckon that those people are going to
have a little bit of a run with some
people particularly very ignorant people
very young people who have been told
about the Holocaust and then go online
and see some things that tell them
there's another story and then they are
trying to weigh this up and they
seriously think but there is a
counter-argument you know and if that
can happen with something that is one of
the most provable things in history then
you can bet it's the case with things
that are much less common knowledge
and and and that is that is a that is a
massive issue and again how do you
divorce that from the people who are
going for the lols you know sick as that
is because there will there is obviously
and a lot of the reprehensible stuff
that happens online there is a
significant amount of that yeah I think
I think we've probably both have a
similar sense of I mean some people call
it the sense making crisis I quite like
that word like what is true seems to be
I don't if you de Greve it to me at
least feels like the if there's a
generator function of many of the other
problems that we're seeing cascading
through society that one seems to be at
the core I remember something you said
in that first interview which I think
was a really great way of summing it up
it's like we cannot imagine not only can
we not imagine kind of a way of
addressing these truth claims we can't
even conceive of who that might be like
yeah who could possibly have that
authority to make those judgments which
I mean I don't see I don't see a way out
I don't see an obvious way out of this
kind of spiral we all have to
concentrate on doing it as well as we
can and as hygienically as we can in the
areas we know most about oh that's
that's that's where you start and by the
way another one which I try to practice
myself but is is not to enter the
speculation in an area if you don't know
just keep out of it don't you know not
everyone has to say everything out loud
all the time there's a rule of thumb
that's not popular of course it it
doesn't awful lot of good if you admit
the nature of a conundrum out loud one
thing I don't think has got enough
attention in recent years is the extent
to which no public discussion is
genuinely taking us forward on main
platforms and
genuinely worried about this that no
discussion show on the BBC or anywhere
else actually solves anything doesn't
even get close and what's the reason for
that the reason is that that's not the
aim anymore the aim is to have a piece
of theater the aim is to claim you've
held politicians to account the aim is
to throw up some some heat and and
everybody who goes on goes on with a
specific agenda which generally is not
to do with trying to get things moving
forward so with the covered issue
you just know that the different
politicians have been waiting until they
can make political capital one direction
or another and you know all of the
commentators and all of the content
providers who have just been using it to
shore up something they already had to
sell and my point is on a whole range of
issues what if we approached it
differently like what if I hate to cite
the Guardian but you did and I'm amazed
that they did something so comparatively
praiseworthy but let's say that instead
of having the vicious vicious nasty
fight about trans which is predicated on
either you know mmm clap along to trans
child getting hormone blockers or you're
killing trans people or making trans
people get murdered or making trans
people kill themselves how about we had
the discussion on yeah actually there
are there are competing virtues and
competing claims and they don't all
rubble on well they rub against each
other quite nicely and aggressively in
places we need to work out a way through
this to concede that isn't nothing to go
on to almost any other issue I did this
in a strange death of Europe on the
migration issue I said as as Aristotle
shows us if you've got two apparent
virtues and they're in competition you
should recognize it and you should
workout which is being misapplied or
misunderstood I said it on the migration
issue I said it repeatedly that that's a
chat that's a a contest between between
mercy
and and that is mercy to people coming
in and justice not least justice to the
people in the countries are coming into
a competition between justice and mercy
is worth acknowledging and worth
drilling down on just like on a much
less important level it's worth drilling
down on the extent to which trans treads
over women and treads on to gay people
but where is a discussion
apart from on a few internet sites a few
forums and a few people who write about
this stuff where is the discussion on
that why do we keep being derailed on it
why do we keep being distracted why do
we never get forward on these things why
don't we solve anything and and I I'm
just stunned by the fact that on issue
after issue on the ones I know about
that's what I recognize and then I speak
to people in different disciplines and I
discover they have exactly the same
experience what's really interesting I
mean this covers it sort of like the
generator function seems to be kind of a
zero-sum game in some ways that everyone
is involved in this kind of zero-sum
game and we've kind of talked about a
little bit of friend of mine Peter
Lindbergh came up with the idea of an
anti debate which is instead of this
sort of zero son who's trying to win is
like can you have a debate where you're
trying to build on each other's
propositions or because because there
does seem to be a bug in the source code
of what the information economy or the
media or something that is that is
constantly cascading us down to the
lowest common denominator it has an
awful lot to do with the fact that no
good faith is attributed to opponents
and I don't know how we get out of that
because we're all guilty of it I've
probably done it myself at the Guardian
today as on many other occasions I it
it's very hard to I mean to just sort of
steal man as it were what some of my
critics and critics of others doing just
on the ones I write about I I think to
steal man
their argument and to be kind to them in
their analysis they think that people
like me should not write or speak about
the things we do because they genuinely
think that it is somewhere too close to
there for somewhere down the line people
doing something terrible because of it
and they they believe that if if certain
arguments are opened up and allowed to
go on we will get to for instance
fascism quite fast and in a way I
understand the fear because we all have
it with political opponents to some
extent I'm no fan of Jeremy Corbyn and I
think that if Jeremy Corbyn had been
Prime Minister elected last December and
had asked me particularly me in my own
case to stay in my house for the
foreseeable future I would have had a
hard time trusting him on that because
I'd have been wondering what it was he
wanted to do down the line and what
other liberties he would take away and
so on so we all have those fears of
opponents it's just that I think
something about the the the information
technology age has meant that we're
always closer to that than we used to be
you know there are really terrible
reprehensible figures from the right and
the left that I've seen across our
continent
who worried me enormous Lee but not
disproportionately unless I think
they're coming close to something like
power and and and and so you have to and
I try to keep it in some kind of context
but maybe all of the time what is
happening is that we are attributing to
other people a proximity to the worst
things all the time and that that makes
it impossible to ever act in a spirit of
generosity towards people with whom you
differ politically and you know as I say
what I'm guilty of of all guilty of it
to some extent but it does make it
almost impossible because you have to be
able to attribute good motive at some
point not least to people when they know
more than you about a subject now that's
an absolutely key one you save a lot of
time among other things but but for
various reasons we have become almost
incapable of doing that of practicing
that
and somehow we've got to learn to
acquire that at least in some
circumstances because we don't have the
time I mean we just no individual has
the time to work out everything for
themselves you know we can work out as
much as we can for us if we can't work
out everything and we have to have some
type of trust in our societies and in
individuals and in institutions and in
experts which is why there salmon this
is this is an important moment because
what we have been going through in
recent recent weeks may well just be the
prelude to something and something much
more confusing where we will need good
sense making equipment and we'll need
some amount of trust even more than
we've needed it in the weeks leading up
to now yeah thank you Douglas
I'm going to use this for a very clumsy
segue to to mention but all of that you
just opened up is really really
interesting
like we've been kind of drilling down
into that like the psychological
dimension why why certain parts of our
system are activated by these kind of
arguments I don't think there's a way of
getting through it without at least
understanding kind of some of our basic
kind of wiring evolutionary wiring to
see to see kind of threats for example
and an understanding that sense making
is gonna like real sense making is going
to involve some kind of trust and it's
going to involve some kind of
vulnerability or at least a safe space
being created for the discussions well
but also that thing I mentioned earlier
the absolutely crucial element of making
one's peace with the world to some
extent and the world as it is you know I
mean accepting that there will be I mean
it's easier to do this by the way on an
individual level and a historical level
it is to do it on a sort of species
level because I think there's a disjunct
I mean maybe this is subject from other
time there's a disjunct between
explaining
to people themselves on those terms and
the manner in which we feel ourselves to
be and what I mean by that is if you say
to people look we are we are hard-wired
to follow this sort of behavior it is it
can be both true and inadequate to
explain ourselves in the manner which we
experience ourselves in the world as
living so we might for instance think
well I know that's the case with other
people but it's not the case with me and
and there's something in that that
disjunct that I think is interesting a
friend of mine use a prison doctor for
many years made the very interesting
observation some years ago that he spoke
to prisoner after prisoner who said that
they had fallen into the wrong crowd and
although he met so many people had
fallen into the wrong crowd he never met
the crowd and and just as people don't
say I was the crowd that other people
fell into so when you explained the way
in which we behave on a kind of genetic
level there's a there's a there's
there's something that is is missed
which is why as I say I'm much more fond
of explaining it in a way in historical
terms or saying no these are the things
that have always been with us and and
then to an extent making your peace with
that doesn't mean you don't do anything
about it but it means you have a
reasonable a reasonable approach to
things that you can't do anything about
you know you'll never you'll never get
rid of the hucksters completely you'll
never get rid of the wires and you'll
never get the world without hate no so
have have reasonable aspirations it
seems to me great a very good place to
end on Douglas thank you very much for
joining me know it's a great pleasure
good to be with you again
rebel wisdom was set up to make sense of
the world at a deeper level than the
mainstream media it was built for these
times of crisis and change which is why
we want to do what we can to meet the
challenge of the times more films and
also for our rebel wisdom members weekly
sense-making calls with our amazing
interviewees and also we're introducing
the wisdom gym a place to practice some
of the skills that we've talked about on
the channel thanks for watching and see
you soon
[Music]